Finding Aid for William J. Norton papers, 1906-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William J. Norton papers 1906-1987 1916-1972
Norton, William J. (William John), 1883-1975.
85343 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan, social worker, executive vice president of the Children's Fund of Michigan, and chairman of various relief commissions during the depression. Materials relating to his welfare activities, his interests in mental health and the work of the American Red Cross, and his general interest in the field of social work; also papers detailing his activities with the Detroit Prismatic Club; essays concerning the legislation of prohibition in Michigan; and photographs and sound recordings.
4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection has been received in several accessions from William J. Norton and his heirs (donor number 4192 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William J. Norton, social worker, was born in Maine, April 8, 1883. After graduating from Bowdoin College, he entered social settlement work in Brooklyn, New York and later Cleveland, Ohio. In the period 1913-1917, he organized the Cincinnati Council of Social Agencies; and Community Union and Detroit Community Fund. In 1929, he became executive vice president of the Children's Fund of Michigan, a post he held until the dissolution of the fund in 1954. During the Depression he also served as chairman of the Detroit Emergency Relief Commission (1931), as chairman of the Michigan Emergency Welfare Relief Commission (1933-1938). Norton was also president of Oakland Housing Inc., a low income housing project originally funded by James Couzens and the Rural Rehabilitation Division of the Federal Emergency Relief Administration. After the 1943 Detroit race riot, Norton was appointed chairman of the Mayor's Interracial Commission. Other governmental and private social welfare posts he held included president of the National Conference of Social Work (1928); trustee of the McGregor fund; chairman of the Detroit Chapter of the American Red Cross (1944-1945); chairman of the Michigan State Hospital Commission (1938-1945) and chairman of the Michigan Department of Mental Health (1945-1947). Norton died in 1975.
The William J. Norton collection relates mainly to relating to his welfare activities, his interests in mental health and the work of the American Red Cross, and to his general interest in the field of social work. The collection has been divided into seven series: Biographical Material and Correspondence, Presentations and Essays, Articles, Fiction Writing, Social Work Organizations, Audio Tapes and Photographs, and Other Materials.
Subjects:
Charities--Michigan.; Child welfare.; Children's Fund of Michigan.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Labor--Michigan.; Mental health--Michigan.; Norton, William J. (William John), 1883-1975.; Prismatic Club (Detroit, Mich.); Prohibition--Michigan.; Public welfare--Michigan.; Red Cross and Red Crescent--Michigan.; Social service--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fund raising.; Hulbert, Henry Schoolcraft, 1869-1959.; American National Red Cross.; Hospitals--Michigan--Detroit.; Children's Hospital of Michigan.; Cottage Hospital (Grosse Pointe Farms, Mich.); Detroit Osteopathic Hospital.; Florence Crittenden Hospital.; Grace Hospital (Detroit, Mich.); Harper Hospital.; Mount Carmel Mercy Hospital.; Oakwood Hospital (Dearborn, Mich.); St. Joseph Mercy Hospital (Pontiac, Mich.); St. John Hospital (Detroit, Mich.); Woman's Hospital of Detroit.; Providence Hospital (Southfield, Mich.); Physicians--Michigan.; Nurses--Michigan.; Sinai Hospital of Detroit.; Health care--Michigan.; Medicine--Michigan.; African Americans--Michigan.
Contributors:
Atwood, Orville E., 1880-; Barnard, Harry, 1906-1982; Brennan, John V., 1872-1971.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Couzens, Frank, 1902-1950.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Cowgill, Ella Lee.; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Frankensteen, Richard T. (Richard Truman), 1907-1977; Haber, William, 1899-1988.; Hilberry, Clarence Beverly, 1902-; Johnson, Fred.; Kelly, Harry F. (Harry Francis), 1895-1971.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Washington, Forrester B.; Westbrook, Lawrence, 1889-1964.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical material and correspondence
  Biographical Material and Correspondence includes letters from Orville Atwood, John V. Brennan, Prentiss M. Brown, Frank Couzens, James Couzens, Ella Lee Cowgill, Frank Fitzgerald, Richard T. Frankensteen, William Haber, Clarence Hillberry, Fred Johnson, Harry Kelly, Alexander Ruthven, Forrester B. Washington, Lawerence Westbrook, and G. Mennen Williams. Some other correspondents are included but most of the material concerns Norton's social work.
  - Biographical Material (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1906-1975, 18 folders (Box 1)
- Presentations and essays
  Presentations and Essays help to document Norton's views on public relief during the depression, his interest in the improvement of mental health facilities in Michigan, and the activities of the Children's Fund of Michigan.
  - Speeches undated (Box 1)
  - Speeches 1932-1958, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Essays undated (Box 1)
  - Essays incomplete undated (Box 1)
  - Essays 1907-1960, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers presented at Acanthus and Prismatic Clubs undated (Box 1)
  - Papers presented at Acanthus and Prismatic Clubs 1951-1963, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Book reviews undated (Box 2)
  - Handwritten incomplete manuscripts undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Manuscript on attempts to legislate prohibition in Michigan (draft) undated (Box 2)
  - Manuscript on the Children's Fund of Michigan (draft) undated (Box 2)
- Articles
  Articles contain published articles authored by Norton. These further illustrate Norton's position on various social issue as well as his standing within the social work community.
  - "The Class History" in Bowdoin Orient, Brunswick Maine, July 7, 1905 Commencement Number (Box 2)
  - "Chief Kohler of Cleveland and His Golden Rule Policy", in Outlook, November 6, 1909 (Box 2)
  - "Social Work in A Competitive World" in The Survey MidMonthly, July 15, 1925 (Box 2)
  - "Social Work Grows Up" in Survey Graphic, November, 1927 (Box 2)
  - "The Detroit Riots---and After" in Survey Graphic, August, 1943 (Box 2)
- Fiction
  Fiction Writing contains plays and an unpublished novel written by Norton.
  - The Crime Wave, a play, 1921 (Box 2)
  - Mirrors of Detroit, a play, 1922 (Box 2)
  - The Millennium, a play, 1923 (Box 2)
  - The Eternal Struggle, unpublished novel, undated (Box 2)
- Social work organizations
  Social Work Organizations concerns Norton's work with various agencies in Detroit including the Children's Fund of Michigan, the Detroit chapter of the Red Cross, the Greater Detroit Hospital Fund and the Prismatic Club of Detroit. Printed reports from social agencies in Connecticut, Kansas, Minnesota, New York and Ohio are also included.
  - Child Welfare League 1968 (Box 2)
  - Cincinnati Council of Social Agencies
    - Social Engineering in Cincinnati, 1919 (Box 2)
  - City Club of Chicago City Clubs of America, 1922 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut State Council of Defense Report on War Chest Practice, undated (Box 2)
  - Detroit Chapter of the American Red Cross
    - Memoranda 1960-1972 (Box 2)
    - Red Cross Courier, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Club 1967 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Community Union 1920 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Council for Youth Service 1936 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Public Library 1965 (Box 2)
  - Greater Detroit Hospital Fund
    - Contracts with Hospitals 1954 (Box 2)
    - Development 1950 (Box 2)
    - Finances 1950 (Box 2)
    - Governing Documents 1931-1956 (Box 2)
    - History 1949-1956 (Box 2)
    - Hospital Facilities for Negroes, 1948-1952 (Box 2)
    - Interracial Hospital 1948-1954 (Box 2)
    - Membership undated (Box 2)
  - Kansas Public Welfare, April, 1920 (Box 3)
  - McGregor Fund 1955-1972 (Box 3)
  - Meeting Programs (Various Organizations) 1923-1964 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Advisory Committee on Education 1936 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Department of Mental Health Reports 1947-1961 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Emergency Welfare Relief Commission
    - Westacres, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan League for Human Services 1987 (Box 3)
  - National Conference of Social Work August 1924 (Box 3)
  - New England Home for Little Wanders Little Wander's Advocate, 1920 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1925-1972 undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Detroit Free Press articles concerning retarded children in Michigan, 1955 (Box 3)
    - Obituaries of W.J. Norton 1975 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania Charity Organizations 1914-1921, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The Philanthropic Boards Established by John D. Rockefeller, 1916 (Box 3)
  - Prismatic Club of Detroit
    - Histories (Box 3)
    - Membership lists (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1905-1908, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Review of 1944-1945 season and miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Programs 1924, 1932-1972 (Box 3)
  - Russell Sage Foundation Bulletins 1912-1916 (Box 3)
  - Rochester NY Chamber of Commerce Solicitations Wise and Unwise, 1917 (Box 3)
  - State Conference of Charities and Corrections (Minnesota) 1919 (Box 3)
  - Testimonial Dinner, William J. Norton: Scholarship in Social Work May 1954, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Torch Club of Detroit 1951-1972 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Committee on Social Problems 1934 (Box 3)
  - Wayne County Board of Supervisors 1936 (Box 3)
  - Welfare League of Louisville The Community, 1920 (Box 3)
  - Calendars of Meetings and Conferences 1945-1950, 1954-1957, 1959-1960, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
- Audio tapes and photographs
  Audio Tapes and Photographs contain special format materials such as reel-to-reel and cassette tapes. Some tapes are unidentified or partially identified. Photographs of Norton at fund-raisers and other functions are included. The series also contains photos of many of the hospitals in the Detroit as well as portraits of other social activists from Detroit.
  - Audio Tapes
    - Recording of interview of Judge Phiny Marsh by Norton and Mark Beatty, re: Tracy McGregor (Box 4)
    - Recording of interview of James Redhouse, re: Tracy McGregor; side 2, W. J. Norton Speech to Prismatic Club, "Saga of a Foundation Executive" November 6, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Recording of Survey Meeting (Box 4)
    - Unidentified, 5 tapes (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Fundraising dinners 1942-1968, undated (Box 4)
    - Groups 1939-1966, undated (Box 4)
    - Hospitals (Detroit area) undated
      - Children's Hospital (Box 4)
      - Cottage Hospital (Box 4)
      - Detroit Osteopathic Hospital (Box 4)
      - Florence Crittenden Hospital (Box 4)
      - Grace Hospital
        - Main (Box 4)
        - Northwestern (Box 4)
      - Harper Hospital (Box 4)
      - Jewish Hospital (Box 4)
      - Mount Carmel Hospital (Box 4)
      - Oakland Hospital (Box 4)
      - Providence Hospital (Box 4)
      - Saint Joseph Pontiac (Box 4)
      - Saint John's (Box 4)
      - Women's Hospital (Box 4)
    - Individuals (not Norton) undated (Box 4)
    - Portraits and informal photographs of Norton 1952-1964, undated (Box 4)
    - Portrait of Norton undated (Folder 1)
    - Sketch of Norton 1937 (Folder 1)
- Resolutions
  The resolutions honored the work of Norton as head of the Children's Fund of Michigan and following his death in 1975.
  - Detroit City Council Resolution in memoriam William J. Norton, 1975 (Folder 1)
  - Michigan Senate Resolution honoring the Children's Fund of Michigan 1954 (Folder 1)
  - Michigan Senate Resolution honoring William J. Norton 1973 (Folder 1)
Related Materials
The records of the Children's Fund of Michigan are also available at the Bentley Historical Library.